Guide to the John C. Kilgo Records and Papers, 1888 - 1970 (bulk 1894-1920)
Duke University. University Archives
John C. Kilgo records and papers 1888 - 1970 (bulk 1894-1920)
Kilgo, John C. (John Carlisle), 1861-1922.
12.5 linear feet Extent: 10,000 Items
Duke University. University Archives
John C. Kilgo served as President of Trinity College (Durham, N.C.) from 1894 to 1910. The John C. Kilgo Records and Papers contain correspondence, sermons, lectures, articles, newspaper clippings, memorabilia, printed matter, and scrapbooks pertaining to Kilgo's career as an educator, as President of Trinity College, and as a Bishop of the Methodist Episcopal Church, South. Subjects include Kilgo's educational philosophy, family affairs, Duke family philanthropy and the financial state of Trinity College, union of Methodist churches, Kilgo's election as bishop, and controversies in which he and the College were involved, including the Gattis vs. Kilgo controversy and the John Spencer Bassett Affair concerning academic freedom. English.
UA.03.54.0001
Language: English.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
The collection is open for research.
The clippings files (Folders 137-144) contain brittle newsprint and may require reformatting before use. Please contact University Archives staff before visiting to use this portion of the collection.
Provenance
The John C. Kilgo Records and Papers were acquired by the University Archives, date unknown.
Biographical Note
College president, Methodist clergyman and bishop, born Laurens, South Carolina, July 22, 1861. A.M., Wofford College, 1892; D.D., Randolph-Macon, Wofford, 1895; L.L.D., Tulane, 1910, Trinity, 1916. President, Trinity College, Durham, NC, 1894-1910; Bishop, Methodist Episcopal Church, South, 1910-1922. As an educator, Kilgo was an advocate of a strong public school system, but thought that higher education belonged in co-ed colleges conducted under Christian auspices.
Kilgo's father, James Tillman Kilgo, was a circuit riding Methodist preacher, and his mother Catherine Mason, of Fairfield County, S.C., was related to the prominent Mason family of Virginia. There were five children, three boys and two girls. John's early education took place in those communities where his father preached. He attended McArthur Academy in Limestone, and Gaffney Seminary, and in 1880 enrolled at Wofford College. Eye problems caused his withdrawal at the end of his sophomore year. While at McArthur, a school organized along the lines of a strict English academy, he absorbed the code of strict rules and discipline that characterized his own career as an educator. After withdrawing from Wofford, Kilgo taught school in Clio, S.C., and was licensed to preach in May of 1882. From then until 1888, he rode a circuit in South Carolina, becoming known as an outstanding preacher. In December of 1882, he married Fannie Natt Turner, of Gaffney, S.C.; they had five children.
In 1888 he was made financial agent of Wofford College, and was able to continue his education. He received the M.A. from Wofford in 1892, and was appointed Professor of Philosophy and Political Economy. It was during his time at Wofford that he developed the educational philosophy he was later to put into practice at Trinity. Kilgo thought that true higher education could be secured only in institutions conducted under Christian auspices; such schools should be coeducational, as separate women's colleges at that time tended to be inferior to men's.
In 1894, at the age of thirty-three, Kilgo was elected a delegate to the General Conference of the Methodist Episcopal Church, South, becoming one of the youngest men ever sent. His reputation led an editor to to call him "one of the most useful and popular members of the South Carolina Conference." In July of that year, Kilgo was elected President of Trinity College in Durham. He took up his post the next month, establishing a reputation as a gifted preacher and educator. Methodists around North Carolina were ready to support their college and see it grow, and it was during Kilgo's tenure that Washington Duke took a great interest in the college's affairs. As President, Kilgo spoke out on many controversial topics, including the role of the state in education, academic freedom, and the education of women.
In 1910, he was elected a Bishop of the Methodist Episcopal church, South, and resigned as President of Trinity. He continued, however, to take an active role in the affairs of the school, becoming first a member, then the chairman, of the Board of Trustees. He lived in Durham until 1915, when he moved to Charlotte in order to more easily carry out his responsibilities as a bishop. In 1917, following a controversy over student behavior, Kilgo severed his connection with the College. Kilgo was a member of the Education Commission of the Methodist Episcopal Church, South, which founded and incorporated Emory University.
His health began to fail late in the decade, and in 1920 he was relieved of his episcopal duties. On August 22, 1922, he died in Charlotte, and was buried there.
[Portions of this text are taken from Elizabeth H. Copeland's sketch of Kilgo's life, ca. 1984]
Collection Overview
The John C. Kilgo Records and Papers contain correspondence, sermons, lectures, and articles, both manuscript and printed, along with newspaper clippings, memorabilia, and scrapbooks pertaining to Kilgo's career as an educator, as President of Trinity College, Durham, N.C., and as a Bishop of the Methodist Episcopal Church, South. Subjects include Kilgo's educational philosophy, family affairs, Duke family philanthropy and the financial state of Trinity College, union of Methodist churches, Kilgo's election as bishop, and controversies in which he and the College were involved, including the Gattis vs. Kilgo controversy and the John Spencer Bassett Affair concerning academic freedom.
The records and papers are organized into ten series. The first series, Correspondence, contains Kilgo's correspondence regarding Trinity College, Wofford College, the Methodist Church, the Bassett Affair, and the Duke family. The Sermons and notes series features handwritten and typed sermon manuscripts and other notes, mostly undated. The third series, Lectures, addresses, and writings, includes manuscripts and published material relating to Trinity College, eulogies, citizenship, the South, education, the Methodist Church, and religion. The Methodist Episcopal Church, South series contains Board of Missions Financial Statements, resolutions, addresses, and related materials. Personal and biographical materials include clippings, biographies, genealogical information, printed matter, and financial documents. This series also features modern materials, such as family correspondence of Kilgo's descendants, that were added to the collection.
The Trinity College records series features building specifications, Kilgo's inaugural address, printed matter, and materials relating to the Clark vs. Kilgo case (1898). The next series, Gattis vs. Kilgo, Duke, and Odell contains documents relating to the 1905 slander suit brought by Thomas J. Gattis against Kilgo, Benjamin N. Duke, and W. R. Odell. The seven Scrapbooks contain clippings of Kilgo's articles and sermons, pages cut from the Bible and hymnals, book reviews, and other items. The Additional materials include a catalog of Kilgo's library, a card inventory of his records and papers, and reference notes detailing press attacks on Kilgo, Trinity College, and the Duke family from 1891 to 1906. The Oversize materials series contains documents from the preceding series in the collection stored in oversize containers.
Subject Headings
Academic freedom; Bassett, John Spencer, 1867-1928; Coeducation; Duke, Benjamin Newton, 1855-1929; Duke, Washington, 1820-1905; Duke University -- History; Duke University. President; Duke University -- Presidents; Educational fund raising -- North Carolina; Gattis, Thomas Jefferson; Kilgo, John C. (John Carlisle), 1861-1922; Methodist Episcopal Church, South; Methodist Episcopal Church, South -- Clergy; Methodist Episcopal Church, South -- Education; Odell, W. R.; Trinity College (Durham, N.C.) -- History; Women -- Education (Higher) -- North Carolina -- Durham; Clippings; Scrapbooks
Contents of Collection
- Correspondence, 1891-1922 and undated
  Subjects present in the Correspondence series include affairs at Wofford College, Kilgo's appointment to the presidency of Trinity, unification of the Methodist Church, fund-raising, educational reform, and Kilgo's election as Bishop. The items include Walter Hines Page's address at the dedication of the Trinity College Library (February, 1903) and Washington Duke's letters of December 1896, and April 1903 concerning his gifts to the College and the status of its women students. Correspondents include Joseph Gill Brown, Wallace Buttrick, William Preston Few, James H. Southgate, Washington Duke, and Robert Lee Flowers.
  The correspondence is indexed in the University Archives card catalog.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - Jan. 1891-Sep. 1898 (Box 1, Folder 1-7)
  - Oct. 1898-May 1903 (Box 2, Folder 8-13)
  - June 1903-Aug. 1907 (Box 3, Folder 14-19)
    President Theodore Roosevelt's 1905 speech at Trinity College included in folder 16.
  - Sept. 1907-May 16, 1910 (Box 4, Folder 20-25)
  - May 17, 1910-June 1918 (Box 5, Folder 26-31)
  - July 1918-April 1920 (Box 6, Folder 32-37)
  - May 1920-Aug. 1922 (Box 7, Folder 38-40)
  - Undated correspondence (Folder 41-42, Box 7)
- Sermons and notes, 1882-1918 and undated (Box 7)
  Manuscripts and notes for sermons, mostly undated. Two notebooks list sermons and dates given; three volumes are titled "Sophomore Bible," "Junior Bible," and "Senior Bible" from 1895-1896, and may have been intended for those classes at Trinity College. Sermons and notes are hand-written or typed on loose papers and in a variety of bindings. Notebooks contain full sermons on particular topics with biblical passages, or sermon outlines. Some of the books contain miscellaneous notes.
  - Sermons, 1885, 1898-1900 (Box 8, Folder 43)
    Includes A Sermon on the Witness of God's Spirit (1885), Annual Opening Sermon preached by Dr. John C. Kilgo Before the Student Body of Trinity College (Sept. 17, 1899), Christmas Sermon (1899), and other sermons.
  - Personality and Progress, preached by Eugene R. Hendrix, ca. 1901 (Folder 44, Box 8)
  - Sermons, undated (Folder 45-46, Box 8)
    Includes Dr. Kilgo's Sermon before the Student Body, The Prepared Man, Beware of the Pharisees, An Apostate Church, and other sermons.
  - Notes, undated (Folder 47-50, Box 8)
  - Notes, undated (Box 9, Folder 51)
  - Record of Sermons, 1882-1889 (Folder 52, Box 9)
  - Sophomore Bible, 1895-1896 (Folder 53, Box 9)
  - Junior Bible, 1895-1896 (Folder 54, Box 9)
  - Senior Bible, 1895-1896 (Folder 55, Box 9)
  - Outlines of sermons, 1898 (Folder 56, Box 9)
  - Sermon notes, 1907, 1911-1913, [2 volumes] (Folder 57, Box 9)
  - Sermon notes, [1914?] (Folder 58, Box 9)
  - Sermon notes, 1918 (Folder 59, Box 9)
  - Sermon notes, [1918?] (Folder 60, Box 9)
  - Psalms of David, undated (Box 10, Folder 61)
  - Sermon notes, Wofford College, Spartanburg, S.C., undated (Folder 62, Box 10)
  - Sermon notes, undated, [15 vols.] (Folder 63-75, Box 10)
  - Sermon notes, undated, [6 vols.] (Box 11, Folder 76-80)
- Lectures, addresses, and writings, 1895-1916 and undated (Box 11)
  Manuscript and typed lectures, articles, speeches, reports, and notebooks. Most of the materials are undated, some may have been titled by Kilgo, and some have supplied titles. Articles include The North Carolina Conference and the Twentieth Century Movement, The American Democracy, Physical Culture at Trinity College, and The Meaning of a Larger Endowment for Trinity College. Titled notebooks include: Development of American Methodism; Christology, 1895; Key to map of the Western North Carolina Conference, M.E. Church, South; and Slavery in America. Copies of published articles include: Christian Education: Its Aims and Superiority, [1896?]; Our Duty to the Negro, 1903; American Commercialism; The Silent South, [1907]; Francis Asbury, [1916]; A Plea for the Union of Methodism in America, 1906; The Value of Endowed Colleges. Other writings treat inter-collegiate athletics, the history of Vanderbilt University, educational philosophy, why he severed his connection with Trinity College, and talks to students and fellow Methodist clergy. Among the manuscripts are writings on Washington and B. N. Duke and eulogies for J. H. Southgate, Joseph F. Bivens and others. The notebooks contain material on a variety of subjects: notes for a lecture on Robert E. Lee; theology; genealogical notes on the Burton (or Bruton?) family; Washington Duke, and other subjects.
  - Trinity College, 1898-1916 and undated (Box 11)
    - Administrative addresses, 1907, 1912, and undated (Folder 81, Box 11)
    - Addresses to the student body, 1898-1900 and undated (Folder 82, Box 11)
    - Baccalaureate addresses, 1896, 1903, 1916, and undated (Folder 83, Box 11)
    - Bassett Affair: speech to the Board of Trustees, Dec. 1903 (Folder 84, Box 11)
    - Chapel talks, 1898-1900 and undated (Folder 85, Box 11)
    - In Memory of Mr. Washington Duke: exercises held in Craven Memorial Hall, Trinity College, Durham, N.C., June 4, 1905; Memorial Address: President John C. Kilgo, 1905 (Folder 86, Box 11)
    - The Lines of the Future Development of Trinity College, undated (Folder 87, Box 11)
  - General lectures and addresses, undated (Box 11)
    - Eulogies and biographical addresses, undated (Folder 88, Box 11)
      Includes eulogies for Charles Brantley Aycock, Joseph Francis Bivins, Washington Duke, Bishop William Wallace Duncan, Bishop James Henry McCoy, John B. Robins, and James H. Southgate. Also includes a biographical address about Benjamin Duke.
    - Citizenship, the South, and other topics, undated (Folder 89-90, Box 11)
    - Education, undated (Folder 91-92, Box 11)
    - Methodist Church, moral, and religious, undated (Folder 93-94, Box 11)
  - Published addresses and articles, 1897-1916 and undated (Folder 95, Box 11)
  - Notebooks (Box 12)
    - The Development of American Methodism, undated (Folder 96, Box 12)
    - Key to map of the Western North Carolina Conference, Methodist Episcopal Church, South, undated (Box 12)
    - Education and business, undated (Folder 97, Box 12)
    - Gardening, memoranda, and other notes, undated (Folder 98, Box 12)
    - Notes on the Bible, undated (Folder 99, Box 12)
    - Notes on "Christology," 1895 (Folder 100, Box 12)
    - Notes on Methodist conferences, 1906-1910 (Folder 101, Box 12)
    - Notes on Robert E. Lee, [ 1907] (Folder 102, Box 12)
    - Notes on slavery in America, undated (Folder 103, Box 12)
    - Sketches of Biblical characters and of Robert Burns, undated (Folder 104, Box 12)
    - Travel notes: British Isles, France, Italy, undated (Folder 105, Box 12)
    - Commonplace books, undated, [2 vols.] (Folder 106-107, Box 12)
    - Lecture and miscellaneous notes, undated, [6 vols.] (Folder 108-112, Box 12)
- Methodist Episcopal Church, South records and printed matter, 1915-1919 and undated (Box 12)
  Board of Missions Financial Statements, 1915-1916 (6 vols.); newspapers; forms for recording minutes; resolutions, addresses, and related materials. Additional materials documenting Kilgo's involvement with the Methodist Church can be found in the Sermons and notes series and in the Lectures, addresses, and writings series.
  - Addresses, undated (Box 13, Folder 113)
  - Certificates and printed matter, undated (Folder 114, Box 13)
  - District lists and documents, 1918-1919 and undated (Folder 115, Box 13)
  - Printed matter [oversize] (Folder 116, Box 13)
  - Resolutions and declarations, 1919 and undated (Folder 117, Box 13)
  - Financial statements (Box 13)
    - Board of Missions, 1915 (Folder 118, Box 13)
    - Board of Missions, 1916 (Folder 119, Box 13)
- Personal and biographical materials, ca. 1888-1970 and undated (Box 13)
  Correspondence with Kilgo's descendants; biographical data on Kilgo; Moravian Church literature; postcards and memorabilia from a trip to Japan; a Greek Bible; bills, receipts, check stubs, ca. 1910 - 1920; newspaper and magazine clippings concerning the controversy over the Mecklenberg Declaration, Methodist Conference activities, Kilgo's speeches and articles, conditions at Trinity College, and other subjects. The series also consists of some anonymous poetry and miscellaneous printed matter.
  - Biographical and genealogical documents, [ 1910] and undated (Folder 120, Box 13)
  - Cards and circulars, 1895-1907 and undated (Folder 121, Box 13)
  - Family letters, 1922-1944, 1965, 1970 (Folder 122, Box 13)
  - Japan, travel and preaching, 1917 (Folder 123, Box 13)
  - Moravian Church, 1931-1934 (Folder 124, Box 13)
  - North Carolina Baseball Association, Articles of Agreement, [ 1901] (Folder 125, Box 13)
  - Personal and genealogical documents, 1913 and undated (Folder 126, Box 13)
  - Poetry, 1888-1911 (Folder 127, Box 13)
  - Printed matter, advertisements, and circulars, 1895-1919 and undated (Folder 128, Box 13)
  - Printed matter, 1901-1908 (Folder 129, Box 13)
  - Bills and receipts, 1910-1920 (Folder 130-134, Box 13)
  - Check stub book, 1921 (Folder 135, Box 13)
  - The New Testament in the Original Greek. London: Macmillan, 1907. Student's edition with lexicon. (Folder 136, Box 13)
    Contains marginal notes made by Kilgo.
  - Clippings, unprocessed (Oversize 14, Folder 137-144, Box 13)
- Trinity College records, 1894-1910 and undated (Box 13)
  Report of the Board of Trustees concerning the charges brought against Kilgo by Trustee Justice Walter Clark, 1898 (2 copies of a bound pamphlet); Trinity College Financial Statement, Inter-State Audit Company, Charlotte, 1917; Washington Duke Memorial Fund, subscription and donor books, 1905-1908 [2 vols.]; C. Hook and other architects' specifications for Kilgo's residence and for a new dormitory building at the College; report of the Board of Visitors, ca. 1900; program and seating chart from President Few's Inauguration; manuscript and typed copy of Kilgo's inaugural address, 1894. Miscellaneous printed matter, including a broadside on fraternity corruptions, debate programs, and ephemera.
  - Building specifications, 1898 and undated (Box 15, Folder 145)
  - Clark vs. Kilgo, 1898 and undated (Folder 146, Box 15)
  - Inaugural address, [1894] (Folder 147, Box 15)
  - Printed matter, 1898-1910 and undated (Folder 148, Box 15)
  - Synopses of faculty lectures and student papers, undated (Folder 149, Box 15)
- Gattis vs. Kilgo, Duke, and Odell, 1905 and undated (Box 15)
  Hearings at the Wake and Granville Superior Courts, and a North Carolina Supreme Court appellate brief, concerning the slander suit brought by Thomas J. Gattis against Kilgo, B. N. Duke, and W. R. Odell.
  - Record in case of T. J. Gattis versus J. C. Kilgo, B. N. Duke, and W. R. Odell, before His Honor Frederick Moore, Judge, and a Jury at the July (Special) Term, 1905, of the Superior Court of Wake County, Vols. 1-4. (Folder 150, Box 15)
  - Accusations and defense, ca. 1905 (Folder 151, Box 15)
  - Statement, June 1905 (Folder 152, Box 15)
  - Self-Defense, Aug. 1905 (Box 15)
- Scrapbooks, 1906-1910 and undated (Box 15)
  Scrapbooks contain newspaper clippings of articles, sermons, and other activities of Kilgo, including a 5-part article on female education, written in Spartanburg, pages cut from the Bible and hymnals, book reviews, and other items.
  - Scrapbooks, 1906-1910 and undated, [7 volumes] (Oversize 16, Folder 154-155, Box 15)
- Additional materials, 1936, 1946, 1950 (Box 15)
  This series consists of materials added to the collection that describe Kilgo's records and papers, as well as materials written about Kilgo and Trinity College. These materials include a card catalog of the library of President Kilgo, which was presented to Duke University Library, and an early card inventory of the Kilgo records and papers created by the Manuscripts Department. Also included are reference notes compiled by Nannie Tilley in 1936, documenting the newspaper coverage (ca. 1891-ca. 1906) of the Bassett and Gattis cases and the relationships between Kilgo, Trinity College, and the Duke family.
  - Catalogue of Library of President Kilgo Presented to Duke University, ca. 1946 (Box 17-18)
    Kilgo's Library may have been presented to Duke University sometime after 1924. The volumes in the library were cataloged around 1946, and seem to have been incorporated into both the Divinity School Library and the general collection of the Duke University Libraries. Many of the titles listed in the Kilgo Library card index can be found in the Duke University Libraries online catalog.
  - Card inventory, 1950 (Box 17-18)
  - Reference notes from newspapers, 1891-1906 (Box 19, Folder 156)
    These references to articles about Kilgo were collected in 1936 by Nannie M. Tilley of the Duke Manuscripts Department. The notes refer to articles written between 1891 and 1906 in Webster's Weekly, the Progressive Farmer, the News and Observer, the Biblical Recorder, the Raleigh Christian Advocate, the Concord Times, and the Raleigh Post. Subjects of the articles include the Bassett Affair and the Gattis vs. Kilgo slander suit. Many of these articles attack Kilgo and Trinity College for accepting trust money from the Duke family, while others defend the actions of Kilgo and the College.
- Oversize materials (Box 19)
  Materials from the preceding series are stored in oversize containers:
  - Methodist Episcopal Church, South records and printed matter (Oversize 20, Box 19)
    - Printed matter [oversize] (Folder 116, Box 19)
  - Personal and biographical materials (Box 19)
    - North Carolina Baseball Association, Articles of Agreement, [ 1901] (Folder 125, Box 19)
    - Personal and genealogical documents, 1913 and undated (Folder 126, Box 19)
    - Printed matter, 1901-1908 (Folder 129, Box 19)
    - Check stub book, 1921 (Folder 135, Box 19)
    - The New Testament in the Original Greek. London: Macmillan, 1907. Student's edition with lexicon. (Folder 136, Box 19)
  - Trinity College records (Box 19)
    - Printed matter, 1898-1910 and undated (Folder 148, Box 19)
  - Gattis vs. Kilgo (Box 19)
    - Record in case of T. J. Gattis versus J. C. Kilgo, B. N. Duke, and W. R. Odell, before His Honor Frederick Moore, Judge, and a Jury at the July (Special) Term, 1905, of the Superior Court of Wake County, Vols. 3-4. (Box 19)
Related Material
[Forms part of:] Duke University President records.
University Archives, Duke University.
John Spencer Bassett Collection.
University Archives, Duke University.
Bassett Affair Collection.
University Archives, Duke University.
Benjamin Newton Duke Papers.
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.